National Congress of Neighborhood Women Records, 1974-1999
Sophia Smith Collection, Smith College
National Congress of Neighborhood Women records
1974-1999
National Congress of Neighborhood Women
MS 322
144 boxes (58 linear ft.)
Sophia Smith Collection Smith College Northampton, MA
Feminist grassroots network. The primary goal of this organization was to empower poor and working-class women to become community leaders. The collection offers valuable source material for the study of working-class feminist organizing; urban studies; and women in community development. Also documented are the inner workings of grassroots organizing, with all of the personal and political dynamics that come with incorporating a feminist consciousness into an organization, where issues of class, race and ethnicity are acknowledged and openly discussed. Material includes correspondence, publications, funding proposals, photographs and audiovisual material.
The National Congress of Neighborhood Women (NCNW) is a support network for grassroots women's organizations and community leaders dedicated to empowering, and providing a voice for, poor and working-class women working to improve their communities and their own status in low-income urban and rural areas on local, national, and international levels. The history of NCNW begins with the remarkable vision and energy of Jan Peterson, co-founder and long-time director of NCNW, as well as the spirit and commitment of the neighborhood women in the Williamsburg-Greenpoint area of Brooklyn, New York.
Jan Peterson had recently arrived in New York City in 1969 when she joined the Conselyea Street Block Association with neighborhood women of Williamsburg-Greenpoint, a predominantly working-class and mixed ethnic (Italian, Polish, Irish, Hispanic, and African American) area of Brooklyn. Inspired by the community activists of the civil rights movement she had worked with as a volunteer for CORE (Congress of Racial Equality) in Harlem, as well as the burgeoning anti-poverty and feminist movements, she had a vision of creating an inter-racial, multi-ethnic community organization within a poor and working-class neighborhood, similar to the one in which she'd grown up in Wisconsin.
In 1973, at a meeting sponsored by the National Center for Urban Ethnic Affairs, Jan Peterson got together with other grassroots leaders and professional women to plan a national conference of working-class women in Washington D.C. for 1974. It was at their second conference in 1975, that "the first national federation of blue collar, neighborhood women" (National Committee letter, 1977) was founded, with an office established in Williamsburg-Greenpoint. The Brooklyn office would administer both national and local programs in Williamsburg-Greenpoint, serving as a "laboratory" and model for other community organizations. Their primary goal was to empower poor and working-class women to become community leaders -- to give them a voice, and to raise their consciousness of their own power so they would be better able to define and solve problems facing their communities. They aimed to accomplish this through education, as well as job skills and leadership training, always with an emphasis on preserving family and community cohesiveness. In addition, NCNW had a vision of developing a national network of grassroots women to share resources, experiences, and knowledge.
NCNW's flagship program was their community-based higher education program, begun in 1975. Developed in collaboration with local community colleges and with input from the students, courses were designed especially for mature women, most already active in their communities, who had a desire to develop the knowledge and skills necessary to become effective community leaders. Closely tied to NCNW's first employment program, Project Open Doors, courses were supplemented by apprenticeship experience in women's and community organizations throughout New York City. In the 1980s, NCNW expanded its education program to include pre-College adult education courses in literacy, math, English as a second language, and preparation for the high school equivalency degree (G.E.D.). In 1986, NCNW opened the "You Can" Community School, an alternative education, pre-employment and leadership training program for youth.
Another one of NCNW's core programs is the Leadership Training and Support Program, of which an integral part is the Leadership Support Process (LSP) developed by Lisel Burns. Begun as part of the College Program, leadership training and support groups were soon offered as workshops in regional and national conferences, and incorporated into affiliated organizations across the country. The support groups include consciousness-raising to allow neighborhood women to develop an awareness of how oppression based on class, ethnicity, race or gender might impede their sense of empowerment as leaders. For more information on NCNW's programs, see "Series Descriptions" below.
In the early and mid-1980s, NCNW underwent restructuring of its organization in order to expand its national program and lend more support to grassroots women leaders around the country. In 1986, the Neighborhood Women of Williamsburg/Greenpoint (NWWG), an independent but affiliated organization was created to administer the local programs including the education programs, employment training, leadership support, and public housing tenant training and organizing. The national office continued to network with, and offer training and technical support to, other grassroots women's organizations ("affiliates") across the country, in urban as well as rural areas, including Appalachia, the Pacific Northwest, and the Dakota Nation. Members exchange information and experiences including tenant organizing, the formation of rural land trusts, reforming public schools, and creating leadership support groups.
In 1985, NCNW members attended the UN Third World Conference on Women in Kenya, where they noticed a lack of involvement by poor and working-class women. With other grassroots women from developed and developing countries, they created a network called GROOTS International (Grassroots Organizations Operating Together in Sisterhood). NCNW is the North American representative. GROOTS was successful at bringing grassroots women's representation to the UN's Fourth World Conference on Women in Beijing in 1995. NCNW also has gained consultative status with the United Nations and has opened an office there, enabling them to more easily disseminate information and resources to policy makers and grassroots community leaders and to ensure that low-income women have a voice in community development policies around the world.
The National Congress of Neighborhood Women Records consist of 58 linear feet, dating from 1974-1999, and document the early history of the organization, the growth of its local and national programs, and the development of a national and international network of poor and working-class grassroots women over a 20 year period.
Types of material include correspondence, memoranda, records of the administrative boards and committees, annual reports, material from national conferences and planning meetings, funding proposals, program descriptions and reports, writings on the history and programs of NCNW, publications, articles, research papers, files on affiliated organizations, printed material, photographs, and audiovisual materials.
Since this is a continuing collection of an existing organization, it is necessarily incomplete, with many gaps in the records, particularly those documenting programs still active. The bulk of the material in this processed portion dates from 1975 to 1990. Focusing on the years before the split between the national and local administrations, these records document the formation of core programs in education, employment, and leadership support, as well as the development of a national community development agenda. Also well represented are local housing and tenant programs of the 1980s, the Resource Center, and networking and involvement in the early years of the international women and development movement. In SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION, there is only a small amount of documentation of NCNW's local affiliate, the Neighborhood Women of Williamsburg/Greenpoint. However, their involvement in local programs from 1986 to the early 1990s is represented within SERIES II. PROGRAMS.
It offers a rich source of material on the formation of a successful national organization based on feminist principles and with a grassroots, working-class base. It also offers a fascinating view of its inner workings, with all of the personal and political dynamics that come with incorporating a feminist consciousness into an organization, and where issues of class, race and ethnicity are acknowledged and openly discussed. Through personal stories, shared in workshops, support groups, conferences, meetings, and writings, we are offered a unique perspective on the women's movement.
In addition, there is a treasure trove of subject files on women's issues, grassroots organizing, and community development. Included are numerous published and unpublished writings by NCNW members and others on topics such as class, working-class feminism, ethnicity, female poverty, and women and community development. There are also files on women's and community activist organizations, many in the New York City area, as well as NCNW affiliates nationwide, and international organizations.
Note on Arrangement of the Collection:
The inter-relatedness and continuing evolution of the NCNW programs creates a challenge in attempting to organize the records in our typical hierarchical arrangement. The programs of NCNW are best viewed as a web, not distinct projects. The community and economic development vision/agenda of NCNW, for example, influenced projects in many program areas, including leadership and employment training, housing projects, and of course, international programs in community development. Identifying where one project ends and another begins can be problematic, changes in funding often affected the name of the project, as well as its staffing and scope. Wherever possible, the original organization of records has been retained. For example, in SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION, the Central Chronological File and the Development files have been kept intact. But for the most part, records were received in various states of order, in which case the archivist imposed an organization that seemed to be consistent with the original provenance of the records.
This collection is organized into five series:
I. Administration
II. Programs
III. Organizations
IV. Photographs
V. Audiovisual Material
Information on Use
Terms of Access and Use
The processed portion of the records is open to research according to the regulations of the Sophia Smith Collection, with the following restriction: Researchers must sign an Access Agreement Form agreeing to not identify individuals who are still living without their written permission.
Unprocessed accessions are closed.
Additional Formats
Selections from the National Congress of Neighborhood Women Records can be viewed in the Web exhibit Agents of Social Change: New Resources on 20th-century Women's Activism.
Many of the videotapes from this collection have been digitized and are available to view online.
Additions to the Collection
Periodic additions to collection are expected and are not reflected in this record.
History of the Collection
The National Congress of Neighborhood Women began donating its records to the Sophia Smith Collection in 1986.
Recent additions to this collection are unprocessed and are not reflected in the finding aid.
Search Terms
Burns, Lisel; Gilkey, Bertha; Noschese, Christine; Peterson, Jan; National Congress of Neighborhood Women--History--Sources; Neighborhood Women of Williamsburg/Greenpoint (Brooklyn, N.Y.); NGO Forum on Women, Beijing '95; World Conference to Review and Appraise the Achievements of the United Nations Decade for Women (1985: Nairobi, Kenya); New York (N.Y.)--Social conditions--20th century--Sources; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.)--History--20th century--Sources; Community development--New York (State)--New York--History--Sources; Ethnicity--United States--History--Sources; Feminism--United States--History--Sources; Housing--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Leadership in women--United States--History--Sources; Minority women--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Neighborhood--New York (State)--New York--History--Sources; Occupational training for women--United States--History--Sources; Poor women--United States--History--20th century--Sources; Urban renewal--United States--History--Sources; Vocational guidance for women--United States--History--Sources; Welfare recipients--Employment--New York (State)-- New York--History--Sources; Women--Education--United States--History--Sources; Women--Employment--United States--History--Sources; Women--Housing--History--Sources; Women in development--International cooperation; Women's rights--Congresses; Women--Services for--United States--History--Sources; Women--United States--Social conditions--20th century; Women--United States--Economic conditions--20th century; Working class women--United States--History--Sources
Additional Information
Related Material
Selections from the National Congress of Neighborhood Women Records can be viewed online in the Web exhibit: Agents of Social Change: New Resources on 20th-century Women's Activism.
See also Tamar Carroll's New York City Women Community Activists Oral History Project (Sally Martinez Fisher and Ethel Velez); and the Voices of Feminism Oral History Project (Payne; Miller; Peterson).
For more on the general history of NCNW and Neighborhood Women of Williamsburg-Greenpoint (NWWG), see the Neighborhood Women website, the Neighborhood Women Youtube page and the Women and Social Movements Web site.
Bibliography
A number of articles have been published on the history of NCNW and its programs and many are included in this collection. Below are a few of the more comprehensive articles:
Belenky, Mary F., "The National Congress of Neighborhood Women," in A Tradition That Has No Name (NY: BasicBooks, 1997)
Haywoode, Terry L., "Neighborhood Women Keeping it Together," City Limits, April 1985
Haywoode, Terry L. and Laura Polla Scanlon, "World of Our Mothers: College for Neighborhood Women," Women's Studies Quarterly 1993: 3&4, pp. 133-141.
- SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION 1974-1996, 24 linear ft.
  This series is arranged in 16 subseries: General; Corporate Board of Directors; National Advisory Board; National Steering Committee; Task forces; National meetings and conferences; National meetings and conferences; Local; Staff; Individuals; Buildings; Public relations; Membership; Central chronological file; General correspondence; Subject files; and Development.
  This series documents the founding and early planning of NCNW; funding of its programs; as well as the inner workings and interpersonal relations within the organization. Since its founding in 1975, the national programs have been administered by NCNW's Corporate Board of Directors and National Advisory Board; later the National Steering Committee (which replaced the NAB in 1982). These bodies are made up of members representing affiliated organizations across the country. Jan Peterson has been Executive Director of the National office in Brooklyn since the founding, except from October 1977 to January 1980 when Christine Noschese took over, and from 1983 to 1985 when Alice Quinn and Jan Peterson served as co-Directors. A Local Advisory Board and Local Director administer the Brooklyn programs (under the Neighborhood Women of Williamsburg/Greenpoint since 1986).
  The General files include official documents; records documenting the NCNW's organizational structure, including the re-structuring in 1982, and the separation of local and national operations in 1985-86; and annual reports, circa 1975-84. For additional reports, see the Executive Directors' reports under Individuals; Corporate Board of Directors; and reports on programs in SERIES II. The records of these national administrative bodies (the Corporate Board of Directors; National Advisory Board; and the National Steering Committee) include correspondence; meeting minutes; biographical information on members; reports; and committee files. These records offer valuable insight into the founding, planning, and development of NCNW. Notable Board members and Steering Committee members represented here include Maryland Congresswoman Barbara Mikulski; St. Louis Housing activist, Bertha Gilkey [see also SERIES II. PROGRAMS-Housing and tenants]; Eleanor Holmes Norton; Crystal Lee Sutton (the "real Norma Rae"); author Nancy Seifer; Rona Feit, founder of the National Women's Political Caucus; and Marie Cirillo, founder of the Woodland Community Trust in Tennessee. For more information on these and other members, see Individuals. The National meetings and conferences subseries includes the first planning meetings held in Washington, 1974-75, as well as NCNW-sponsored national conferences and conventions held thereafter. These files include additional material on several Board and Steering Committee meetings that took place at the national conferences. Types of material include correspondence, programs, agendas, minutes, membership information, notes, and printed material [see also SERIES. IV. PHOTOGRAPHS, and SERIES V. AUDIOVISUAL]. For other conferences sponsored by NCNW, see SERIES II. PROGRAMS - Miscellaneous projects and events; and conferences under specific programs. With the restructuring of operations in 1986, the local affiliate, Neighborhood Women of Williamsburg/Greenpoint, was created to administer the programs in Brooklyn. The subseries Local - NWW/G includes documentation of the early planning before the split [see also General-Restructuring]; administrative correspondence; the Local Advisory Board records; and funding material. Of particular interest is a detailed interview of NWW/G staff by author Mary Belenky done in 1992. These are administrative records only. Records on specific local programs are filed in SERIES II.
  The Staff subseries includes staff logs, meetings, files on training, office procedures, personnel policies, and other documents related to the inner workings of the Brooklyn office. Sensitive personnel material such as evaluations and salary information has been removed and is closed to research. The Individuals subseries contains files on staff, administrators, members, and others affiliated with NCNW. These include biographical information as well as working files on a variety of projects and topics. Types of material include correspondence, reports, papers, drafts, notes, clippings and printed material. There is a substantial amount of material for each of the Executive Directors (Jan Peterson, Christine Noschese, and Alice Quinn) as well as for Lisel Burns, Leadership coordinator. Additional working files for individuals are filed under specific programs in SERIES II. PROGRAMS. Additional biographical information can be found in this series under Membership, National Corporate Board, National Advisory Board, and National Steering Committee.
  Public relations includes administrative files of the PR coordinator; press releases, clippings, and other publicity by and about NCNW; files related to the production of NCNW's newsletter, and other publications; and general descriptions of NCNW, primarily untitled excerpts that were probably used for funding proposals and reports. [See also SERIES II. PROGRAMS-Resource Center which includes records on outreach and networking efforts through "Project Interchange."] For more writings about NCNW and its programs, see Development-Proposals; and SERIES II. PROGRAMS-publicity, reports, papers, and proposals under each program. Additional documentation of NCNW's networking can be found in the Membership subseries which includes lists and completed membership forms of NCNW affiliates, providing interesting background information on community activists and organizations. Additional material on NCNW affiliates can be found in SERIES III. ORGANIZATIONS.
  The Central chronological file dates from 1973 to 1989 and include most of the outgoing correspondence, publicity, minutes, agendas, internal memoranda, reports, and papers, produced by the NCNW national office during that period. Much of the material here is duplicated elsewhere in the collection, but this file provides the most comprehensive overview of the organization and its day-to-day administration. Of particular interest is the internal memoranda which reveal the inner workings of the NCNW office, the interpersonal relations, as well as the infinite challenges and constraints involved in running a grassroots organization. The General correspondence contains incoming correspondence, dating from 1976 to 1985. Additional administrative correspondence can be found in the Subject files that include administrative correspondence, minutes, draft reports, printed material, and notes. Topics include local, state, and national political contacts; meetings with local community leaders; and legal matters. Additional administrative files can be found under Individuals and in SERIES III. ORGANIZATIONS.
  The Development subseries documents the history of funding efforts for NCNW and includes administrative files, proposals for general operational funding; and files on funding agencies arranged alphabetically. This section includes important material on many of NCNW's programs. Additional funding information for specific projects can be found in SERIES II. PROGRAMS, but since funds from one source were often shared by more than one project, those files are found here under the funding agency. For instance, under New York City-Department of Employment, is material related to CETA (Comprehensive Employment Training Act) funding for several of NCNW's employment programs. Included are records on the legal battle which ensued when the city tried to cut the programs' funding. [See also SERIES II. PROGRAMS - Employment - Project Open Doors; and SERIES IV. PHOTOGRAPHS.] Files related to the funding for curriculum development for the education program as well as for leadership training are under the Women's Education Equity Act Program (WEEA).
- SERIES II. PROGRAMS 1975-1996, 28 linear ft.
  These series documents local, national and international programs administered by NCNW. It is arranged alphabetically (after Support services) by program area, as defined by NCNW for the most part, although some projects are filed together under areas created by the archivist (such as the Community and economic development, International, and Youth). Under each program area, individual projects are arranged chronologically from date of inception. Many NCNW projects are interrelated as changes in funding often required shifting program parameters and staffing. These relationships are explained in the descriptions below, and cross-references appear throughout the folder list. Types of material include program descriptions and publicity; administrative records such as correspondence, reports, proposals, minutes, and funding information [see also SERIES I. ADMINISTRATION-Development]; surveys; training materials; conference materials; resource files including articles and papers by NCNW members; and files on participating organizations and individuals. Some Program participants' files containing sensitive personal information have been removed and are currently closed to research. These include counselors' intake forms; applications; questionnaires; student evaluations, and some personal correspondence.